Finding Aid for Ann Arbor Human Rights Commission Records 1957-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ann Arbor Human Rights Commission Records 1957-1993
Ann Arbor (Mich.). Human Rights Commission.
12 linear feet
Agency of the city of Ann Arbor established in 1957 as the Human Relations Commission to investigate and deal with issues of racial discrimination in housing and employment. The name of the agency was changed in 1970 to the Human Rights Commission. The scope of the Commission came to include complaints of discrimination against women, gays, and the disabled. The record group provides substantial documentation of issues of racial discrimination in employment and housing in Ann Arbor, Michigan in the period of 1957 to 1993. Included are files relating to the establishment of the commission, minutes (through 1993 with some gaps), memoranda (1968-1970), topical files, early case files (1965-1970), and student intern projects and reports of members of the community practice program within the University of Michigan School of Social Work.
0198 Cc 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were donated by the Human Rights Office of the city of Ann Arbor (donor no. 9060 ) and came to the library in January-February 2001.
The record group is open for research.
The Human Relations Commission was created in 1957 as an agency of the city of Ann Arbor. Established originally to deal with issues of racial discrimination (in housing and in employment), this city agency gradually expanded into areas of discrimination against women, gays, and the disabled. When established the Commission consisted of twelve members appointed by the mayor with the approval of the city council. The aims of the agency were primarily informational and investigative. According to the city code, the commission was "To disseminate information and educational materials; to investigate problems and situations of discrimination; to aid in the coordination of private organizations concerned with human relations; to advise and recommend to the Council the appropriate steps to deal with conditions which strain human relations."
In 1970, Ann Arbor passed a human rights ordinance which provided guarantees against discrimination in housing, employment and public accommodations. Charged with the enforcement of the human rights ordinance was a Human Rights Department. This city department should not be confused with the Human Rights Commission (renamed in 1970 from Human Relations Commission). Primarily because of lack of funding, the Human Rights Department was divested of its department status in 1976. Early in 1978, the department was revived within the office of the city administrator. Currently the department is positioned administratively within the Human Resources Department of the City of Ann Arbor. The Human Rights Commission also continues to perform its investigative and informational responsibilities.
The record group provides substantial documentation of issues of racial discrimination in employment and housing in Ann Arbor, Michigan in the period of 1957 to 1993. Included are files relating to the establishment of the commission, minutes (through 1993 with some gaps), memoranda (1968-1970), topical files, early case files (1965-1970), and student intern projects and reports of members of the community practice program within the University of Michigan School of Social Work.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.). Human Rights Commission.; African Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Black Action Movement (University of Michigan); Ann Arbor (Mich.); Discrimination in education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Discrimination in housing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor (Mich.). Human Rights Commission.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Building deterioration--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Poverty--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- History/Establishment Documents
  - Paper prepared by Marisa Buttrey entitled, "Human Relations in Ann Arbor Eight Years of Human Relations Commission" June 1966 (Box 1)
  - Early reports and meeting minutes 1956-1961 (Box 1)
  - Commission rules and amendments 1957-1969 (Box 1)
- Minutes
  - August 1957-1969, 9 volumes (Box 1)
  - 1970-1983, 9 volumes (Box 2)
    (lacking 1977-1978)
  - 1984-May 1989, 8 volumes (Box 3)
  - June 1989-1993, 1 folders; 4 volumes (Box 4)
- Memoranda (sent to other staff, to other agencies, to commissioners, to mayor and council)
  - 1968, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - 1969 (Box 4)
  - 1970, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Topical Files
  - ADC Mothers (Box 5)
  - AIDS policy 1987 (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor Art Fair 1982 (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor Board of Realtors (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor Chamber of Commerce employment program (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor Community Profile (economic sub-profile) circa 1970 (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor Fire Dept (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor Police Dept (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor "... Poor Families in Ann Arbor" (Robin Barlow) 1964 (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor Washtenaw Conference on Religion and Race (Box 5)
  - Apprenticeship Training Program 1965-1971, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Bautista Affair (Box 5)
  - Black Action Movement 1970, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Black Action Movement, post-1970 (Box 5)
  - Black contractors (Box 5)
  - Black English (Box 5)
  - Black Theater proposal (Box 5)
  - Black trade unionists (Box 5)
  - Blacks United for Liberation and Justice 1970 (Box 5)
  - Blue Magic Band 1975 (Box 5)
  - Briarwood Shopping Center (Box 5)
  - Byrd (David R.) incident 1972 (Box 5)
  - Civil rights (various) (Box 5)
  - Clippings (Box 5)
  - Colorado boycott (Box 5)
  - Community Relations Committee and related (Box 5)
  - Congress of Racial Equality (Box 5)
  - Cooperative Occupational Education/Training, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Demarco dismissal investigation 1969 (Box 6)
  - Detached worker program 1968-1969 (Box 6)
  - Direct Action Committee (Box 6)
  - Divestment of pension funds (Box 6)
  - Education
    - Ann Arbor Board of Education, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor High (Pioneer) School (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor schools (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
    - Committee to Advise Superintendent on Race Relations (Box 6)
    - Education Committee materials 1964-1969, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - High School Human Relations Program (Box 6)
    - Huron High School Black Student Union (Box 6)
    - "Impact of Minority Status ..." (Abramson) (Box 6)
    - Jones School 1967 (Box 6)
    - Police in the School (Box 6)
    - Racial imbalance (Box 6)
    - School attendance boundaries and black enrollment (Box 6)
    - School disturbances (Pioneer/Huron) (Box 6)
    - Suspension data (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous 1964-1969 (Box 6)
  - Elks Clubs (Box 6)
  - Emergency Housing Coordinator 1969-1970 (Box 6)
  - Employment Issues 1969, 1987-1989 (Box 6)
  - Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (Box 6)
  - FAIR (Future Adults Interested in Intergroup Relations) (Box 6)
  - Gay Liberation (Box 6)
  - Gays and Ann Arbor Police (Box 6)
  - Handicapped persons issues (Box 6)
  - Housing
    - Ann Arbor Housing Commission (establishment of) (Box 7)
    - Ann Arbor Housing Commission-general, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Compliance Review (Box 7)
    - Fair Housing ordinance 1961-1968, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Housing Code enforcement January 1967 (Box 7)
    - Housing Commission (HRC) 1963-1967 (Box 7)
    - University of Michigan student studies of housing issues (Box 7)
  - Human Relations
    - Human Relations in Ann Arbor 1956 (Summary report and Full technical report (Box 7)
    - Human Relations in Ann Arbor; a community profile 1967 (Box 7)
  - Human Rights Commission (formerly Human Relations Commission)
    - Accelerated Programs 1969-1969, 1 folders; 3 volumes (Box 7)
    - "Ann Arbor and the 'Great Explosive Mixture'" 1969 (Box 7)
    - Annual Report 1971 (Box 7)
    - Community Profile, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Discriminatory classified advertisements 1971-1973 (Box 8)
    - Employment Committee and employment issues (Box 8)
    - Human Relations general 1957-1966 (Box 8)
    - Human Rights Study 1986-1988, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Informal hearing survey 1983 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Personnel material (Box 8)
    - Reports and funding proposals, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Reports (staff and U-M students) (Box 8)
    - Staff retreat 1993 (Box 8)
    - Staffing candidates, criteria, and issues (Box 8)
    - Status of Commission's Efforts 1967 (Box 8)
    - Walk-in Office (Box 8)
  - Human Rights ordinances and related 1969-1978, 1 folders; 1 volumes (Box 9)
  - Lansky's Junkyard (Box 9)
  - Little Angels Nursery School 1973 (Box 9)
  - Mace, Use of (Box 9)
  - Manpower Development programs (Box 9)
  - Minority contractors (Box 9)
  - Model Cities program and proposals, 3 volumes; 3 folders (Box 9)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (Box 9)
  - "Negro Employment in Ann Arbor: 1956-1964" (Box 9)
  - Operation PUSH 1976 (Box 9)
  - Packard-Beakes bypass 1967-1972 (Box 9)
  - Photographs (Box 9)
    Photographs of various meetings and discussion groups; also photos of a run-down inhabited house, probably in Ann Arbor.
  - Police-Community relations 1964-1970, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Police-Community training (Box 10)
  - Police Review Boards (Box 10)
  - Police Use of Weapons and Force 1975 (Box 10)
  - Population distribution and related (Box 10)
  - Program prospectus 1968 (Box 10)
  - Pump n' Pantry shooting and aftermath 1976, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Rent supplement program 1967 (Box 10)
  - Sexual harassment policy 1995 (Box 10)
  - Sexual preference and related (Box 10)
  - South University incident, summer 1969 (Box 10)
  - Step-up program 1969 (Box 10)
  - Summer Youth Employment program, 1 volumes; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Summit Park (name changed to Wheeler Park) (Box 10)
  - Take Our Daughters to Work Week 1993 (Box 10)
  - Tenants rights (Box 10)
  - Title I meeting (Box 10)
  - University of Michigan and Human Relations Commission (Box 10)
  - University of Michigan-Black housing unit issue (Box 10)
  - Washtenaw County Citizens' Committee for Economic Opportunity, 5 folders (Box 11)
  - Washtenaw County construction program (Box 11)
  - Washtenaw County welfare (Box 11)
  - West Park incidents 1968-1970 (Box 11)
  - Youth miscellanea (Box 11)
- Case Files
  - Numbered complaint files, 52 folders (Box 11)
  - Case miscellaneous (Box 11)
  - Progress reports on complaints 1965-1970 (Box 11)
- University of Michigan School of Social Work Community Practice Program
  - Student Intern Projects and Reports 1964-1971 (Box 12)